so hi everyone thank you very much for coming
along to um our magnet seminars um it's another
good turnout for our um eu and eastern hemisphere
uh time slot and so for those of you who haven't
actually joined our seminars uh before and we
have presentations that are on the order for
about 30 minutes give or take and we just kindly
ask that you keep your microphones muted during
the presentation so it's not to disturb the the
presenter and if you are having problems with
uh your connection if you try turning your mic
microphone and your video off that can improve uh
the connection um after the the presentation we'll
have a chance for a 10-15 minute um question and
discussion session if you don't want to unmute to
ask a question you can just type it into the chat
window and i can read it out for you and as always
we've got life going on in our background so
if you have to to go halfway through the seminar
that's fine it's not a problem just um just get up
and go uh and once everything once we've had our
friend are finished um there'll be a chance for
a bit of a catch up at the end um because i think
a few faces that not everybody has seen for quite
some time so we've got a bit of a social uh at the
end and this part is is not recorded so um it's
a lot more uh informal so and today i'm really
pleased to say that we've got andy harris from la
trobe university in melbourne australia and today
he's going to be talking about um some of his work
um in archaeology and magnetism uh in in africa
and so i will hand hand over to you andy oh
okay can anyone see that perfect okay so um greg
sort of asked me to do this a couple of weeks ago
so it's not going to be the uh it was a little
bit thrown together because i was on holiday
uh last week um so this is sort of going to be a
little bit of an overview of going back to some of
my phd data that i'm sort of beginning to revisit
now that uh i've been stuck in australia for two
years and unable to go to the field and go
excavating um i have been sort of head of
department here at la trobe um in archaeology
for the last three years so i haven't really got
very sort of near the lab uh of late so equally
a big shout out to some a lot of this work is the
work of my uh phd students tom mallett who's just
submitted his phd for review and a site that um
student liz topping is going to be working on
although she's currently sort of stuck back in
england unable to come to australia to sort of get
moving on her phd but um in general i'm going to
talk a little bit about is um the identification
of magnetic reversals and magnetic events
that occur sort of prior to the olduvai subchron
and a little bit about the end sort of reversal
um so i shall sort of like cycle through some of
that so the two sites i'm mainly going to um talk
about when it comes to the sort of more recent
data is kilome caldera which is in kenya which is
um a series of excavations run by the archaeology
department at the university of liverpool
so i've been involved with that site sort of
since about sort of 2010 working at some sites
on the outside of the caldera and then some on
the inside of the caldera which is sort of quite
interesting very very pretty site um and then the
site of dremel and cave which i run excavations at
in south africa which as you can see there doesn't
look much like a cave anymore but we'll sort of go
through sort of um all of that sort of thing so
as far as you know what i do i mean i'm mostly
i'm an archaeologist i run excavations at sites
that's one of my hats and the other thing is
that i've you know for the last 20 or years been
dating early human evolution hominid fossils and
archaeological sequences so i've mostly worked in
south africa but i worked a little bit in eastern
africa so if we look at the sort of dating of
human origins in eastern africa um a lot of the
fossils you find in sediments that sit between
various types of volcanic tuff and other volcanic
layers which can often be argan argan dated um
at quite high resolution depending on you know
how quick stuff was deposited in some
cases if chemical fingerprinting is used
rather than direct dating and magnetostratigraphy
is um you know sometimes used sometimes not used
in circumstances probably where it would have been
really useful to use it when i see a lot of papers
um and you know it's often just a you know a block
of a block of black and a block of white and not
a lot of data sort of included in the papers a
lot and often the reversals are in quite sort of
low resolution so you can see a site here which
is in eastern eastern lake takana in northern
kenya which is something i did about 10 years
or so ago now and you can see that it's sort of
the bottom of the older eye um but the switch
between the actual reversal is really just it
just flips like that in the sort of sequence even
if it's done at sort of relatively high resolution
there's a few sort of older little flips um
that you know could be things but it's just
the one odd sort of uh direction sort of facing
the other way so it's really hard to sort of say
um you know this is sort of an example
of another one that q before in kenya so
you can see here that there's you know perhaps the
suggestion of something else going on towards the
end of the old divide but again it's just sort
of a single sort of couple of samples and it's
often not sort of well refined and so this is what
we often see in the sort of published sequences
for the sort of region um in some cases you
can get some sort of high resolution stuff but
um so columbia caldera um so it's in
the central rift valley of kenya um
so a little bit sort of quite a
bit further south than lake takana
and as i say it's a sort of unusual sedimentary
sequence so you can see this is looking from
the main site at colombia which is around about
a million years old looking towards the actual
colombae volcano and you sort of travel up over
the crater rim and into the middle where there's a
little little village and there's a whole load of
sequences that are um that have been uh deposited
in there so it would seem that the the oldest
deposits have been argan organ dated to around
about sort of 2.5 million years and then there
are a couple of other argan argon dates one
which was around about 1.81 million years and
one that was around about 1.76 million years so
um we knew sort of immediately that we were
around sort of the area of the upper part of the
old device subron but had the sort of potential to
be able to sort of move down through the sequence
hopefully and sort of build up a record of that so
all those sort of transitions pre the old device
sort of subcron this is using the sequences as
published by singer in 2014 so or his geomagnetic
instability timestar as he calls it um so this
is sort of a project that's going to be done by
liz topping but as i say has been sort of stuck
out of the country so i've sort of been doing
some preliminary work on it and you know this is
very very preliminary it's very thrown together
um but we've got a few more argan argon dates
so this is actually sort of the exposure of the
sequences so it's actually sort of a road sequence
but there's all of these masses tons and tons of
different volcanic layers that sort of um that are
exposed across this road cutting and then there's
another road cutting and then there are some other
exposures exposures which are in the middle of the
the farmers fields and we're still sort of working
out how all of these different exposures sort of
fit together but um this sequence also has
sort of um a change from what's called older
one technology which is this early technology
that starts around about 2.6 million years ago
and the beginning of the schulian technology which
sort of comes in from about 1.8 million years so
from an archaeological perspective we're sort of
trying to understand when does that transition
happen sort of in this sequence so i did a
preliminary field season in 2018 where i took
sort of relatively course course sort of sampling
um and now that sort of i know that probably
this entire sequence has sort of formed over um
probably not much you know maximally probably um
you know what is it maybe maybe 160
180 000 years or something like that
um i'm gonna have to go back and do it in sort
of high resolution uh so the older one sort of
layer itself um we're appearing to be potentially
very lucky here in that it sort of sits just below
this argan argan age of about 1.76 sort
of plus or minus 0.02 million years so
we should be sort of pretty near the sort of upper
old of eye reversal at that point so it was really
sort of a hunting expedition to go and see whether
we could sort of find that um so i sort of tracked
down initially from the site and you can see that
actually there's there's um there's no clear um
normal polarity signal in this sort of part of the
sequence um but there are these departures from
the overall reverse sort of polarity that exists
sort of in these lower layers there is another
sequence which has been dated to 1.81 million
and that's actually got a normal polarity so we
sort of know that aldebar is there and we appear
to potentially have sort of something going on
perhaps that's either happening in the reversal
or a little bit afterwards and what we're going
to be trying to do with this now is obviously try
and link those sequences up to see whether we can
actually expand this out a little bit more sample
down further and see if we can get more of this
evidence of sort of changing sort of polarity sort
of across the across the sort of transition so
i mean if we sort of compare it against this
one which is published from kucertal in 2016
in japan you can see sort of you know some of
the potential fluctuations that we could sort
of be looking at sort of at this period so this
is just very preliminary data that i'm sort of
throwing in there but um in a sense to people
that work on magnetostratigraphy a little bit
more familiar with um the east african sequences
and understanding magnetic reversals and use for
dating sort of there so i'll sort of throw this in
just to sort of set up how that sort of happens in
eastern africa before i talk about south africa
which is sort of what i've mostly worked on
um so we sort of flip sort of about you
know 3 000 kilometers south to south africa
there's a whole series of early human fossils that
occur just outside of johannesburg it's about 40
kilometers north west of johannesburg in an
area that they call the cradle of humankind
it's a unesco world heritage site these days and
i've sort of been working here basically ever
since my master's back in the late 90s initially
i started work up a little bit further north about
at the sites of makapunskrat which um
that's actually where some of the first
paleomag was done on these sites in the 70s by
mcfadden and brock who sort of showed that you
know you could get paleomagnetic signals from
this material some follow-up work in these sites
near johannesburg particularly at stark fontaine
and swat crowns was sort of done in the 80s and
gave very very mixed results that appeared to be
all over the place and you know it was considered
that really perhaps we couldn't get um direct
useful directional data out of some of that stuff
i sort of came along um in the late 90s and
sort of started looking at re-examining some
of these sites so this was sort of prior
to when we really had a lot of radiometric
methods that we could use on dating the
sites and to be honest as a phd student um i
was measuring these things and i kept coming
up with these weird funny directions going left
right and center and i thought i was going mad
and didn't believe myself um and then sort of um
you know kirsh fink and other people who were here
published some data sort of from chrome dry in
2002 which actually as a phd student really helped
me sort of like i'm not going mad this is a thing
so thank you for that um and i basically sort of
expanded my work out from my coupon start working
at stoke fontaine and most of the other sort of
sites and sort of time has sort of gone by um
so the sites themselves are quite unusual so
they're sort of they're caves but they're what
we call paleo caves paleocast so this is the site
of dremel and macondo which is one of the sites
that we excavated and this initially was just
a little hole in the ground and then we sort of
expanded it open and we've actually found this
sort of entire area of the cave but the cave is
being completely de-roofed by erosion and then
there's various secondary processes that have
gone on and all of the sediments have been injured
but that's sort of good for us in the way that we
get these nice sort of sections through it
that we can then use for doing um sort of um
doing the sort of dating work and excavating the
fossils etc so it's a rather unusual setting and
you know i was told sort of when i started my phd
that really it was sort of pointless trying to do
peliomag on these things because they'd all
be the same polarity and you wouldn't get any
data out of them and you had no other methods
of dating it but what i began to find was i
kept coming up with finding reversals in these
sorts of sequences um so actually sort of dating
the sites somewhat difficult so you have the
brexit deposits that most of the fossils sit in
now obviously this forms from collapse and this
is the type of material that people first started
um sampling for doing paleo mag but obviously this
is not a good medium for bellio mag because the
signal is not being set you know it's a collapse
um sequence there's lots of clasps in it and so
it's no wonder that a lot of that early stuff
was actually giving these randomized directions
these days we can try and date these deposits
using electron spin resonance on teeth although
the plus or minuses on that are a little bit large
cosmogenic barrel dating which states quartz which
has its own interesting problems um but you do
get these beautifully laminated siltstone and
sandstone sequences which is a what a lot of what
um mcfadden and brock sampled when they were at
makapanskat and certainly this is the sort of
stuff that we generally tend to target in the
sequences and these are all lateral variations to
the pressure anyway so they're sort of dating the
same sort of time period system stuff is winnowed
from that entrance pressure so we can date this
with polio magnetism cosmogenics and if there's
teeth in there electron spin resonance as well
and then we get the spear thames themselves so
um the speleothems uh in general as long as we
can work you know they often form as these big
basal speleothem deposits and we sometimes get
capping units and sometimes they occur in between
we have to be a little bit careful that we don't
that we know that they formed in the sequence
and aren't secondary and that's caused a lot of
sort of debate and we can do paleomagnetism on
them the remnants that we get from the pellet
from these are always excellent much better
than the sediments unless they're very very weak
um and now they can also be directly dated uni
uranium lead so when i sort of started in the late
90s and early 2000s uranium lead couldn't date
this stuff and so i was flying a little bit blind
as to what i was seeing but now we can actually go
and directly date this stuff and robin pickering
who's now at the university of cape town came and
did a sort of phd a little bit after me dating a
lot of the sequences and one of the beautiful
things about it was that when we started taking
these magnetic reversals and the uranium lead ages
everything began to pair up so it basically first
showed what reversals i was looking at but also
helped to really show that you know the uranium
lead was working really really well and giving
you know sort of ages um as would be expected
some of the first sort of site this was sort of
one of the first sites i think that sort of i
found one of these in and most of the reversals
that we find tend to be in the speed of them
layers these flow stone layers because obviously
they form over a longer period of time than
the sediments do the sediments probably form
quite rapidly so catching a magnetic in river
reversing them is a lot of a little bit harder
um but this is one at gladersvale where we did
have some electron spin resonance and you know
those ages were about 578 to 830 and we found
in this flowstone this reversal which we
could sort of show was the sort of bruins
uh messi alma brood and sort of reversal in there
but a lot of this dating in this early day was
done very coarsely i mean we just took the you
know block of samples and took a few samples and
it's just normal and it's reversed we don't have
things all the way through the sequences which is
sort of what i'm trying to go back and do now um
there's this one which this was originally done
by um by um university of liverpool lab before
i sort of started there um and again this is a
sequence of flow stones they didn't sample the
sediments because of those 1908 that 1980s work
where they thought that the data was going to
be sort of bad and wasn't worth sort of sampling
so they sampled the flowstones and again found a
number of sort of different reversals including
within individual sort of flow stones now this was
originally back then um correlated to the gauss
and sort of mammoth events because there was no
other sort of dating methods to go along with it
other than looking sort of at the fauna this has
been sort of a very important sequence because it
has this skeleton what's called little foot which
is the most complete early hominid skeleton of
oscillopithecus sort of ever ever discovered and
there's a lot this this this this one has given
lots of different ages and has been sort of quite
sort of controversial um and then this is also at
the site of stark fontaine so this is associated
with this fossil here which is called mrs cles
which is one of the most sort of famous sort of
fossils um of oslopithicus africanus this early
uh human ancestor from south africa and there
were some all dsr ages done um but the esr ages
were sort of a lot quite all over the place
and people didn't really sort of trust them um
but again this is sort of a relatively thin
flow stone this was one of the ones that i did
sort of sampling a little bit sort of more
resolution as you can see there's a whole load
i apologize for the nature of this data it's
literally pulled from my phd um and you can see
a number of fluctuations where we've got sort of
the main sequence where the fossils is reversed
and in this sort of capping flow stone we see a
number of sort of fluctuating short sort of normal
back to reverse to the polarity periods
i sort of had a shot in the dark
um when i sort of did this sort of suggested
perhaps this was the reunion events um around
about sort of you know 2.1 2.2 million years
which was partly based on sort of some of
these sort of esr sort of ages that have
been done on the lower part of the sequence
um so more recently you know singer has published
this geomagnetic instability time scale where
he's tried to sort of um put in you know
the updated ages and showing this sort of
quite you know potentially lots of different um
reversal events and sort of sub crons sort of in
this period play prior to sort of older by which
both uh is a good thing for us as archaeologists
trying to date this stuff in the sense that we can
potentially refine the age of stuff but is also a
complete nightmare because we've got to know which
one of these things that we're actually looking at
and what i've begun to realize is that you know
in the old days i used to just say it's normal
it's most likely to be older by because it's
the biggest thing in that time period but i'm
beginning to find out that's not really the case
sort of anymore um 2019 we sort of published this
paper sort of in nature which sort of set up the
chronology for sort of the entire of the cradle
region with uranium lead dating of flowstones and
what we began to find is that what we showed was
that ultimately flow stones were forming in each
of the different caves at exactly the same time
period so you could pretty much go and find a flow
stone in one cave a flowstone in the other and
show that they formed at the same sort of time and
a lot of these flow stones we found were actually
forming around periods where we were getting
reversals so around about two point six one
two point two two point sort of one and and then
around sort of aldevise so um you know there was
a high potential and we'd already knew that there
was some reversals in some of this sort of stuff
and so actually when we went back and say reviewed
this and actually directly dated this sequence um
at stark fontaine with uranium lead we got an age
of about 2.03 plus or minus 0.96 which pretty much
suggests that these fluctuations are probably the
huckleberry ridge which is sort of dated around
about 2.07 million years um and then another
site called malapa where we also showed a normal
to sort of reverse transition in a in a flow
stone um i have actually done this one in much
higher sort of detail now uh and again same dates
sort of with uranium lead about 2.03 2.02 million
years so again potentially suggesting we've got a
flow stone forming in two different caves at the
same time period with the same sort of huckleberry
ridge sort of reversal or events sort of in it um
so if we sort of compare that versus um you know
some of the argan organ ages from singer it's
sort of suggesting here we would state uranium
lead ages that those that sort of event might
be a little bit younger than what's suggested by
2.07 in that um so this is sort of going to be an
interesting thing moving forward is comparing
what we're getting from direct dating from
uranium lead on speleothem versus what we're
getting from sort of argan argon for example
um if we go back to stark fontaine into
that lower deposit where there's the
little foot fossil the direct dates for
um uranium lead there come out at 2.24
2.17 so that sort of around the period of sort
of the fenney subcron reunion sort of period um
so again you know interesting that we're getting
uranium lead dates you know suggesting that these
things are potentially smaller reversals rather
than these sort of bigger periods of time um
uh some sort of other stuff that sort of thrown
insights that i'm sort of hoping to sort of go
back to so this was a cycle gondolin which
i sort of again did during my phd and again
in actual fact the capping flowstone here
had a normal to reverse sort of transition
um it's there's no direct dating
for it but we sort of estimated
the based on the paleomagnetic sequence that
that was sort of the end of sort of olduvai
so i want to sort of try go back and sort of again
sample through that and try and sort of get direct
sort of dating on it sort of ultimately so i can
begin to sort of pin all of these reversals in all
of this bfm sort of down and that's sort of what
i'm sort of in the process of doing now really is
trying to go back to all these sites or go back
to all the samples that are sort of sat in the
lab that i can sort of access at the moment and
try and re-measure them in sort of high resolution
and begin to sort of we've got the uranium
lead sort of dating sequence across the sort
of cradle but we're adding esr ages and then
the paleomag to sort of get a comprehensive
understanding of both the dating of the fossils
but also identifying where magnetic reversals are
sort of throughout these sequences and correlating
them sort of across different sorts of sites um
and you know it's beginning to be quite a
treasure trove of finding these sorts of
uh you know finding reversals in there that we
can get data out of now a lot of this was just
done for dating purposes pure dating purposes i
wasn't really looking at it in terms of well okay
what can this actually tell us about the behavior
of reversals can it tell us that is the data sort
of accurate for doing that so um tom mallett my
sort of phd student has been looking into that
a little bit more and a lot more into you know
what's holding the remnants in this material
because in some cases you know the stuff looks uh
the the mineralogy doing basic stuff doesn't look
very different but you get some that work really
well and some that sort of the data looks sort of
terrible um so that sort of brings us to dremelen
which is the site that i sort of run and excavate
sort of now so there's sort of two sites here
there's the main quarry which is where all the
hominids come from which is the younger site
and then there's the condo which is this that
site i showed you sort of earlier on um which
is a little bit um older um so i haven't done
i've got all the samples to sort of redo this so
this is this is dremel in the condo so we've got
sort of a basal spill esm here that's dated by
uranium lead to about 2.664 you see it's got a
little quite a big plus or sort of minus on that
and um and then we've got a whole lot of sediments
with fossils sort of overlying that and then we've
done esr a little bit for higher up that comes at
about 2.71 so they're both pointing to a period
sort of around that sort of 2.6 2.7 million year
sort of mark um some very preliminary did
some very preliminary sampling of this um
because it's hard to get samples out of this so
you tend to do sort of um sparsely separated ones
to see whether there's anything to look at there
before you go and then sort of start trying to
get full sort of sequences out of it because
it is you know it's a hard sort of rock
um material there's a lot of fossils in here but
we appear to have sort of normal priority sort of
in the bottom of the sequence and sort of reverse
sort of in the top so this was sort of one of the
first ones where we were beginning to find well
okay we'll get perhaps we can also find these
reversals if we're lucky in the sediment sequences
rather than just in the um in the speed of thems
which potentially might give us some sort of
higher resolution in these sorts of reversals so
i have a sort of big full sequence of this
in the lab ready to sort of cut up and
go back and sort of re-measure to sort of confirm
our you know suspicions that this is actually the
sort of um this is the gauss matayama boundary
at about 2.61 which i actually again i did find
what i thought was that at a site of makapunskat
back when i did my phd but again i didn't have
any sort of dating work to sort of go with
it at the time it was just a hypothesis
adrenaline main quarry um which you can see
here it's called dremel and main quarry because
um line miners came and mined out the stalagmites
and stalactites and the basal flowstone from here
in the late 19th century in early 20th century
and was used in the gold extraction process so
a lot of these sites have been mined for the
stalagmites in the past and so that's done a
couple of things it creates problems because it
disconnects stratigraphic sequences sometimes um
but it also means we get access to um areas where
there's fossils in that we wouldn't have done
if it hadn't been sort of mined out adrenaline
we're quite lucky because there's a whole series
of in-situ deposits that sit against one wall of
the pellear cavern so we have a complete sequence
through from the basal spelifem all the way sort
of to the roof that we were able to sample through
um sort of back the first it was it's sort of been
most well known for dnh seven which is this uh
the most complete paranthropus robusta skull ever
discovered this is sort of this weird side branch
in our evolution that basically has these big jaws
eating hard objects sort of boobs um and but then
sort of more recently we excavated and found
in 2018 dnh 154 which is the most complete male
version of that species and in 2015 we found this
little sort of juvenile cranium which the dnh-134
that we published in science showing it's the
oldest evidence for homo erectus sort of anywhere
in the world so again this sort of work started
in just sort of trying to date these fossils more
than anything else when i started here in 2010
there weren't sort of any dates for the science
um so as i say we sort of published this in
science in 2020 showing sort of that these three
different species australopithecus homo erectus
and practice were sort of living in the landscape
around the same sort of period of time um and
also showing that sort of at this sort of age
2.04 to 1.95 million which i'll show you how we
got to that is sort of the oldest example we have
of homo erectus sort of anywhere sort of in the
world the next holders potentially being around
about 1.9 in eastern africa and then the very
beautiful stuff from dominici in georgia about 1.8
million years so the sort of sequence sort of this
sort of is just a sort of a simplified sequence
on the back wall of the cave um we have a basal
spillathem uranium lead dated to about two point
uh six seven three million years so it seems that
this bfm and the one up in the condo formed at
the same period of time it appears though
that um that would have formed when there
was no there was no entrance to the surface
there's no sediment really in that spilly fm
and it was probably half a million years before
any sediments that were then actually came into
the cave so unlike macondo where they came in
very soon after the spele of them formed here
they seemed to have taken half a million
years or so before they began to come in
dnh-134 sort of sits at a level that we have esr
dates of about 2.04 million years um and then as
we sort of track and and that's from laterally
there's reverse polarity which makes sense
as we sort of track up through the sequence in
this one section called the walls of jericho which
was so named because when i was trying to take
detailed samples for it nearly fell on me um we
found sort of reversed at the bottom and normal
at the top um when we first sort of sampled it
and then we sort of went back through and sampled
it in sort of quite high detail and found there
was sort of the whole sort of middle section sort
of had this intermediate sort of polarity to it
um so again sort of suggesting that we
had um you know sort of pretty good sort
of resolution sort of through that just sort
of showing this sort of completeness of sort
of what some of the data looks like some of it's
beautiful um some speedy themes work really well
some like this number f here which is the basal
one which because it hasn't got any sediment in it
is awful uh it's obviously sort of uh
we wouldn't trust that sort of data
and this is some of the work that tom's been doing
um on the sort of mineralogical sort of work um
all the data sort of suggests that you know it's
being held by magnetite and probably magimite
um but there's a huge grain size range of very
very lots of ultra fine um sp across to sort of
sd magnetite it doesn't appear to be any evidence
of multi-domain and everything that we've sort of
done so there is a good potential recording signal
there it just appears that there's not a lot of it
um based on some other synchro tron work that
we've done that suggests an awful lot of the stuff
that's there is sort of non-remnants bearing sort
of uh phases and hematite in particular so um this
is sort of the the sequence the walls of jericho
sequence which you can see sort of on the right
and the sort of key to this is actually there's
a little tiny speedo fm layer that sort of runs
through the middle of it and um we actually were
able to get a date off that but we can only date
speed fm layers if they have very high uranium
concentrations in them because otherwise there's
just not enough um sort of lead to basically
measure because it takes so long for one to go
to the other so we're very lucky with this that
we could actually date it and that gave a date
of around 1.96 plus or minus 0.11 million years so
with that date there we had an esr date that's a
little bit lower that came out at around 1.97
million years so we were very very confident
ultimately this was the base um sort of old
divide that we were sort of looking at here and
the intermediate sort of section sort of is over
you know one point sort of 1.2 sort of meters
um of the section and again we did this in sort
of quite low resolution and then came back sort
of and did it sort of in higher resolution and
so this is sort of the sequence that we can see
um with the sort of swing across from um reverse
polarity sort of at the bottom with a bit of
instability the swing across into sort of normal
which is still sort of a little bit unstable and
you can see here one of the things we also did
because there's a lot of question about you
know are these spear themes uh intrusive are they
formed within the sequence we did micromorphology
to show yes it's actually sat in the sequence
but also we did the paleo mag on it showing that
the flow stone has an intermediate polarity
like the sediment sort of above and below it
um and so is part of that sort of continuum across
the the base of um the older sort of reversal
um and this was some stuff that tom sort of threw
together um sort of showing the reversal path uh
based on that sort of data um and just sort of
compared to some of the other sort of published
reversal paths for the olduvai base and there's
some similarity between that and um some of the
other um sort of published uh reversals although
not in sort of we don't have it in quite as high
detail as obviously some of the odp stuff um
so ultimately what i've sort of begun doing now
is really trying to sort of um i'm sort of trying
to sample some of the other sections to sort of
basically try and sort of track this sort of
reversal sort of across the site so that we can
continue to sort of constrain the fossils
to show ultimately it appears that all the
fossils we've sort of excavated so far sort of
sit below this reversal so um you know that's
good because we can immediately say that the
material is sort of older than 1.95 million
years our sort of task now really is to sort
of go back and try and work out well how far
how far back does it go um you know beyond 1.95
we have the esr age of about 2.04 but it has a
plus or minus on it um that sort of suggests
it's probably not older than about 2.28 but
um that's sort of some of the stuff i'm well when
i can get back there i haven't been there for two
years now and i'm beginning to get a bit of cabin
fever at not being able to excavate stuff but
um that's sort of the hope for what we're going
to sort of continue to do there and we're going
to do some other sort of cosmogenic work um but
this is sort of one of the first sites that we've
really been able to show using esr using uranium
lead and the polio mag that we can get these
very good robust solid ages and that sort
of we can get pretty good sort of resolution
of the ages as sort of part of that sort of as
well so so there's uh 20 years of sort of bits and
pieces of work here but i'm sort of now trying to
go back to it and really try to sort of drag the
um rather than just using it as a dating method
but using it to say okay well how you know can we
actually begin to show direct date these reversals
using uranium lead and compare it to other dating
methods and also get higher resolution within
these various sort of reserve reversals and
little sequences that we seem to get popping up
sort of everywhere so that's about my half hour
um this is my sort of wonderful team that sort
of excavates the site of field school students
that as i say i'm really missing my adrenaline
family in south africa and if anyone's seen
what's going on in south africa at the moment um
yeah it's um not good sorry but we're thinking of
lots of our local collaborators at the moment so
um thank you for listening um yeah there you go
excellent thank you very much andy that
was a fantastic talk uh we can give
andy a a virtual round of applause with the uh
zoom reactions um now it's really nice to see
just such a comprehensive uh talk bringing
together a lot of different themes and in
particular i like the idea of really digging back
through old data and getting new insights from
it because that's the kind of stuff that excites
me as well and so we can open the floor to to to
questions so if you have a question you can just
uh raise your hand or or put it into to the chat
you have nobody with any questions at the moment
in silence i'm sure there we go joe's got his
hand up hi joe you can if you meet yourself
uh yeah i noticed on your fork diagram that
seemed to be a bit of a central ridge yeah
do you think the magnetite might be biogenic
um
now you're asking questions um
so i have to say that the the
uh identifying the sort of mineralogy that's uh
holding a lot of these things has been the sort of
trickiest journey of the last sort of
20 years or so of all of this because um
when i first first started certainly um my advisor
was very much of the opinion that this was sort of
multi-domain magnetite and that the signals were
not very good and certainly when you demagnetize
some of this stuff it has really really big sort
of overprints on it sometimes but the overprints
don't seem very stable at all and it's a very sort
of sweet spot for getting the sort of data out
and it doesn't seem to matter what
we do to it it comes out as being
you know the different sites are very similar to
each other but we do get very very different um
data coming from them despite this
what it seems to suggest is that um
we've got magnetite and there's some of it is
in a great grain size range that is holding a
sort of signal but there's not a lot of it when
we put this sort of stuff into a synchrotron
uh you can even really see the magnetite
it was just all showing sort of hematite
um and so and then certain sites like makapun's
clubs um some of the sequences have these sort
of really bright sort of pink colors um that you
know sort of suggest that there's perhaps a lot
of diagenesis sort of gone on i think that
there is in some of the sequences certainly
um some biogenic input um the rest of
it uh but a lot of it i think actually
we've got a lot of very very fine grains which i
think comes from the fact that a lot of this stuff
is um very old and it is in a landscape that's
being sort of repeatedly burnt and is producing
this sort of like fine grain size that's
being sort of washed in a lot of the stuff
is sort of colluvial origin we occasionally get
sites that have what perhaps is material that's
being brought in from a more sort of valley bottom
alluvial setting and that often has a little bit
of a different um mineralogical character to it
ultimately tom actually sort of went out to the us
um to irm to do quite a lot of this stuff because
um my lab's not heavily set up for doing a lot of
the sort of mineralogical um sort of work well
i guess one of the reasons i'm asking is that
magnetic bacteria are known to exist in soil
and body environments yeah pedogenic magnetite
is there hoda valley published a
paper on that almost 30 years ago
but it's not been studied in terms of a source
of fine-grained uh magnetic and or magnetite
and yeah that's where it's coming from it's
not unexpected yeah i mean the thing that
the other thing i notice is that you know again
that um i mean one assumes that it's the same
source material that's in the spelefms as a
contaminant uh certainly in some cases but the
when it's the speleosthem is always giving much
better more stable sort of signals um which
probably maybe it's not undergoing the same
sort of secondary long-term low temperature
alteration that some of the sort of sediments
have been as well and i've also been trying to
understand a little bit more about um you know
these caves are obviously cave sediments that
have been injured by speleothem but so we're doing
a lot of micro morphology to help us understand
has that material been solidified in one
sort of go or has it been solidified perhaps
decalcified and then re-solidified certainly in
some cases it appears that it's just sort of been
it's been interrated and it
sort of remained that way
in in one other cave a site called huskar i've
actually taken sequences in two different parts
of the cave and you can get slightly different
you get different data because one area has had
some secondary sort of decalcification alteration
to it and the other one hasn't um which again
sort of shows how you know you have to be really
careful when you're doing your sampling um to make
sure that you're getting you know material that
has been injured and not decalcified and altered
in sort of any sort of secondary sort of way which
of course when i first started doing all of this
um you know i wasn't really looking for um
ultimately but cool excellent and we can open the
floor to some other questions if anyone has them
if not i can certainly throw a couple euro handy
because i don't see him depending on how this i'll
jump in um i guess so one of the things is with
with some of the expedia therms and stuff that
you have you know there's potential of getting
um high resolution information about the reversals
i mean with the the data that you have um are you
able to see anything about the actual duration of
the reversals well i mean that's the big problem
um you know because obviously you can do that in
younger speedy fm because you can uranium thorium
date them and uranium thorium is exceedingly
accurate whereas the issue with uranium lead
is that you know you date the speed you know if
you date through the spele fm all three ages are
sort of going to overlap with each other um so
you can't use that method to actually refine the
resolution sort of through it you can really just
at the moment date the spelling of them and say
well this is this reversal sort of thing the one
way of potentially doing it um so my colleague
um phil hopley um who's in london we sort of
published a paper from one of the sites but uh
the paleo mag unfortunately and that's really
a thing was not great but he um he actually
they actually he actually went and counted the
sort of annual banding within the spele fm so if
you're able to sort of combine that methodology
with the paleo mag together then potentially you
would be able to sort of give get you know and
you say right well these are annually banded
sequences of formation you could do it that
way potentially i don't know if anyone's done
that but in theory you could sort of do that
the one issue that there is though is that
um you know there's not a lot of stalagmites in
these caves you know stalagmites are the perfect
medium for doing polio mag and getting those high
resolution because they fall at the drip point so
they get everything that's there whereas a lot of
what we've got sort of left to work with are these
what can be massively thick speleothems i
mean there are spillovers that makes cut
that are like five meters thick um you know
absolutely massive but the problem is that they
are you know lateral parts of that sequence and so
if not every sort of drip sort of reach that far
um you're missing sort of parts of the sequence
so it's also a question of identifying where you
might have hiatuses in that and sort of knowing
you know what you might have sort of missing so
i think in some cases if you've got the right
samples it might be possible in other cases
there's a few things that are sort of working
against you um sort of for that and that's a
problem equally i think when um i mean the other
way of doing obviously is also when we i've got a
student working on some of these bsms doing stable
isotopes where we can obviously then also try and
wiggle match the climatic sequences to um that
will also potentially give us ideas of how how
quickly things have formed through the sequences
so yeah so there's a few ways of sort of trying
to sort of uh do it but the other problem with
that is often um and this is one of the things i
didn't i didn't speak about actually which um the
challenges of dating the stuff is that firstly we
need areas of the spillover them that have not
recrystallized the dolomites so these are caves
that are formed within dolomites which means a
lot of the spelems formed originally as aragonite
and then actually then subsequently chris
recrystallizes and altered to calcite so that
can play havoc on those isotopes and dating um
so first we have to sort of find sequences where
that sort of hasn't happened but one of the
things i was very curious about was you know
what what effect does recrystallization have on
the magnetic signal um and there was sort of this
one site malapa there's a piece of the flowstone
at malapa where i was able to sort of do this
where there's a sort of recrystallized part
and we stuck it sort of in the synchrotron
here in melbourne and sort of looked at all of the
where all the iron banding was in the deposits um
and one section of the spillover sort of had a you
know normal polarity and the other part had a sort
of jumble polarity and the actual reason for it
is that during the recrystallization process the
the calcite grains have grown and they've grown
very large calcite grains so what you had is
originally very very small grains and then
as they've recrystallized and they've grown
large they sort of pushed the inclusions up and
around the calcite growing like that so it's it's
basically randomized the magnetic signal because
it sort of pushed it out um like that so so i
did a little bit of work on that which again i
haven't one of the many things i should sit there
and publish at some point um so yeah so that's
sort of some of the other sort of uh i suppose
challenges of maybe you know some of the things
that you also need to look out for if you are
doing work particularly on these old stalagmites
where these sorts of things have sort of happened
yeah cool thank you um i have time for one more
question if anyone has a hand uh so we've got uh
uh tiaboldu um from china so if
you wanna tell me you can ask a
question
uh uh jabba i can't we cannot hear you
no i'm afraid
yeah i think we can hear you now oh great
andy thanks for your talk and uh since your
perimeter patio magnetic results from the south
africa i'm thinking about that recently that
there are some studies claimed that
the south atlantic economy has been
released in the in the south africa area
for tens of tons of meanings of years
so so i saw you also compare your agp movement
with other results so have you considered about
the the inference of essay since data has already
been there for tens of many millions of years
uh i would say i mean the issue is
i mean i just don't have the data to
actually do anything we're comparing that
sort of thing at the moment really so um
obviously i think sort of as we collect more
i mean certainly um yeah i mean that that's
an interesting thing to sort of um sort
of look at once we actually begin to get
um some more high resolution sort of through
these sort of sequences sort of finished but
at the moment i don't really have the data
to um do the compare do anything like that so
yeah thanks well thanks very much that's a really
kind of interesting question an interesting
thing to think about um just how much of
an influence that kind of thing might have
on the records um but i think i'll sort of
um draw through a close there and thank you
everyone for your questions and thank
you andy again for a really great talk
and just before we draw everything to a complete
close um just want to to give a little um reminder
of people for our upcoming schedule so in a couple
of weeks time we'll have uh claire nichols from
oxford giving us a presentation and then a couple
weeks after that we'll have dave heslop from
australia national university and then we'll have
a a short break for uh the iaga meeting so that
we are not um overlapping and then we'll come back
in september and through to the to the end of the
year um we've filled in our schedule uh up towards
the end of the year so if anybody's interested
in giving a presentation where we're opening the
schedule now for 2022 and as always we're really
keen to encourage uh early career researchers
to to promote themselves promote their research
through magnets so if anybody is interested in
giving a presentation please just reach out to us
and and a reminder that all the recordings from
our previous seminars are available through our
threat as well as our youtube channel and i just
want to thank andy once again and thank everybody
for coming to magnets this week and we'll see
you in a couple of weeks thank you all very much